你好黑客
hello hackers
欢迎回到自动化漏洞发掘
welcome back to automated vulnerability discovery
我们在这个视频中讨论的是静态分析
we're talking about static analysis in this video
提醒一下
as a reminder
静态分析是一种在不执行代码的情况下分析代码的技术
static analysis is a technique that will analyze code          without executing it
我们将介绍两种
we're going to cover two types
一种是简单朴素的
one homespun
一种是业界用的大型的工具
one kind of industrial and big and out there
我们从最基本的家庭作坊式的开始
we'll start with the homespun the basics
实际上
turns out
你已经做过静态分析了
you've already done static analysis
你有手动完成过静态分析
you've done static analysis manually
使用像ghidra、binary ninja之类的
using stuff like Ghidra, binary ninja
还有ida，如果你用过的话
Ida if you have used Ida
更重要的是
and more importantly
我说的朴素
when i say homespun
是指像objdump grep和和??
i mean objdump grep sed and and ??
你用过这些东西来查询过ROP gadgets
you have manually used these to search for ROP gadgets
反汇编二进制文件等
to disassemble a binary etc
事实证明，你同样可以
turns out you can do the same
用相同的工具进行自动化的静态分析
you can use the same tools for automated static analysis
事实上，在这个课程中，你手动采取的行动
and in fact the actions that you've taken manually through out the course
通常也可以被自动化
can often be automated as well
通过我制作的一个例子
let's take a very quick look at what i mean by this
快速看一下我的意思
using a example i crafted
我有一个简单的程序
so i have a simple program
它会比较我传入的东西
that compares something that i pass in
它读取1个字节
it reads in 1 byte
然后和常量42比较
and then compares it against a fixed value 42
问题是
and the question of course
我看看它
i can look at this
就知道
and i can figure out
好吧，我看到它
okay well i looked at it
假设我没有源代码
let's say i didn't have the source code
我会反汇编
i would disassemble
编译好的程序的main
just main from the compile program
这是main函数
here's main
我会看看它
i'd look at it
我对它进行逆向工程
i'd reverse engineered it
我会看到cmp指令
i'd see this cmp instruction
0x2a是42的十六进制表现形式
0x2a that's 42 in hex
我看到它
i would see that
我就知道了，我要传入42
and i would say oh okay i need to send in 42
传给compare
i hit compare
他告诉我失败了
and it gives me a failure
哦不是0x42,是0x2a
not hex 42, 2a
好的，成功
all right success
这就拿到flag了
and i have the flag
这是一个使用objdump完成的手工分析
this was a manual analysis done using objdump
我可以自动完成它
turns out i can automate this
想象我是一个自动化系统
so imagine that i'm an automated system
我必须创建一个自动化系统
i have to create an automated system
它会检查二进制程序
that will take a look at this binary
弄清楚答案
and figure out oh what is the answer
所以我创建
so i create
我执行objdump
i do the objdump
我用pipe传给grep
i pipe that through grep
搜索cmp指令
i search for the cmp instruction
只有一个
there's only one
很好，至少main中只有一个
that's nice only one in main at least
然后我做一些后期处理
then i do some post processing
删掉所有16进制数前的东西
to remove everything up to the hex number
太棒了
awesome
这是我要的2a
there's my 2a
现在我们要把它传给echo
now we need to convert it into a into the echo
我们
so let's do
用parallel
use parallel for this
执行 echo -e
do echo -e
加上两个反斜杠
to put two backslashes
这样能转义
so that it escapes the
这样能让反斜杠传到parallel中
so that make a backslash makes it all the way through     parallel
这样就有echo -e \x
and i have echo -e backslash x
跟着输入
and then the input
这将其转换为ASCII字符
boom that converts it to ascii
当然
and of course
如果我手动这样做，能成功
if i manually do that that works
或者我可以将结果发给它，也行
or i can send that through and that works
成了
boom
当然，这是基于人工观察的自动化分析
that is an automated analysis based on manual insights of course
我事先知道要查找cmp指令
i knew that i need to look for the cmp instruction and so   forth
但是我创建了一个自动化的分析
but i created an automated analysis
它能识别程序需要的输入
that managed to do to identify the input that this program needs
只使用objdump grep sed
using objdump grep sed
我们把场景放大
let's scale this out
我创造了很多不同的比较
i created a ton of different compares
每一个需要不同的字节
each one taking a different byte
如果我执行compare_65
so if i of course do compare 65
好的，65
okay six five
这应该是0x41
this should take hex 41
也就是A
which is capital a
它不接收其它数据
and it won't take anything else
当然
now of course
我可以给这些都写个脚本
i can script all of these
在一字节表示范围中，从0到255
i can go from 0 to 255 the whole range of the byte
每一个程序，我都反汇编
and for each one i disassemble the right binary
用我基于grep和sed的自动化分析程序
use my grep and sed based automatic analysis
在这个分析程序中我没有执行任何目标程序
i don't execute anything in that analysis
这是一个静态分析
it's a static analysis
分析后，执行一遍目标程序
and run that back through the binary i was executing
几乎每次都成功
and i get success almost every time
0，第一次失败了
zero zero was a failure
我想知道为什么
i wonder why
我们先不管它
we won't worry about it
但这二百五十多都成
but success on these 250
剩下的失败了
failures on the rest
我们先不管它
we're not gonna worry about it
关键是
the point is
我们成功了很多次
we had many successes
不知道为什么我们失败了那么多次
not sure why we had many failures
我猜是负数的原因
my guess is negative
我定义的char而不是unsigned char
i defined it as a char and not an unsigned char
这有关系吗?
would that matter
是的，这可能有关系
yeah that would probably matter
总之
anyways
关键是使用objdump、grep和sed
the point is using objdump grep and sed
我写了一个静态分析程序
i wrote what is essentially a static analysis
这不是一个复杂的程序
it's not a very complicated one
但也有人写了非常复杂的
but people have written very complicated ones
当可以访问源代码时
when they have access to source code
效果会更好
it can get even better
你可以用grep创建复杂的查询
you can create complex queries using grep
基本上就是在说
that basically say hey
是否存在一个没有长度值的scanf
is there a a scanf that doesn't have a length value
或是否read后，直接strcpy，中间不用strlen检查长度
or is there a read that goes directly into a strcpy that       doesn't have a strlen in between
你可以用grep检查
you can create these with grep
grep是一个非常好的静态分析工具
grep is a very good tool for static analysis
我们看一个真东西
let's take a look at something real
讨论一下codeQL
and we're going to talk about codeQL
codeQL是一种查询语言，用于查询大型代码库中的安全属性
codeQL is a query language to query security properties   on large code bases
它由GitHub创建
it's created by GitHub
或者说它是由GitHub收购的一个小团队创建的
or it was created by a small group that was acquired by   GitHub
它提供了一种查询语言
and it provides a query language
你可以用它描述你想要进行的分析
where you can describe analyses you want to carry out
它会处理所有的疯狂细节
and it will handle all of the craziness of you know
将代码转换成正确的格式等等
getting the code based into the right format etc etc etc
事实上，如果你去lgtm.com网站
in fact if you go to this lgtm.com etc
你可以分析sudo
you can analyze sudo
我们快速做一下
and so let's do that real quick
哦,不
oh no
为什么没切过去
why doesn't this work
好了
there we go
这是codeQL对sudo的分析
here is the codeQL analysis of sudo
放大后
if you scroll in
你可以看到sudo有22个警告
you see there 22 warnings for sudo
往下翻，有一些现成的分析
scroll down there's some canned analyses
它会运行codeql内部有的检查
so it'll run queries that it has internally
我们可以出去看看它们是什么等等
we can out go and look at what they are and so forth
sudo这里主要是一些
mostly here in sudo
你可以调用的危险函数
there's a bunch of these dangrous functions that you can  call
这里有一个整数溢出
and then there's a integer overflow
你对整数溢出很熟悉
you are very familiar with integer overflows
这是乘法导致的可能的整数溢出
as a result of multiplication in fact as well
在内存错误模块讲的
from the memory errors module
sudo的这行代码可能存在乘法导致的整数溢出
turns out there might be a multiplication based integer     error right in this line in sudo
应该检查一下，看看是不是真的有bug
someone should take a look and see if it's really a bug
当然
of course
Codeql是一种静态分析技术
codeql is a static technique
它可能是误报
and it could be a false positive
其他静态分析工具
other tools for static analysis
有很多很多
there are many many many many tools
我会指出几个
i'll point out a couple
一个是angr
one angr
angr是一个Python库
angr is a Python library
它以可编写脚本的方式提供了大量不同的分析功能
that provides a whole lot of different analysis capabilities  in a scriptable way
举个例子
so for example
我们回到这里
if we go here
进入python
and we drop into python
导入 angr库
import angr
加载好程序
load it up
我们可以
we can for example
例如，计算控制流图
compute a control flow greph
哦
oh dear
我们装载的
we're loaded
Angr不像
angr is not as easy to use as
Angr可能是最容易使用的分析框架之一
angr is probably one of the easiest to use analysis            frameworks
但也有一些问题
but there are some gotches
我们要关闭库加载
we're gonna turn off library loading
这样分析就快多了
so that analysis goes much faster
快多了
boom that was much faster
比如
and for example
这里是二进制文件中的所有代码节点
here all of the code nodes in the binary
类似于objdump的功能
similar to what objdump does
但即使去除掉程序中的所有符号，angr仍然有效
but angr works even if the binary is stripped out of all      symbols
而objdump需要这些符号
that objdumpb relies on to extract this
有
there are
看看有哪些函数
see what functions there are
愚蠢的python
Silly python
我们可以
we can do
有哪些函数
what functions
能看到有一个main函数
may we see there's a main function
还有一些其他的
a couple of others
我们还可以做其他各种静态分析查询
and we can do other various static analysis queries
看看哪些代码触及了哪些数据，等等
see what pieces of code touch what data and so on and   etc
例如
for example
angr能在二进制文件中识别出哪些数据
you can see what data angr was able to identify inside the binary
例如在400318处
such as at location 400318
有一个28字节的字符串之类的东西
there's a 28 byte string this sort of thing
可能是这个小程序内置的东西
this tiny binary that's probably some built in stuff all right
有这么个angr，如果你对它感兴趣
so there's angr if you're interested in angr
有一个地方可以了解它
there is a place to get you started
docs.angr.io是对angr的完整介绍
docs.angr.io is an whole introduction into angr
讲述了它的核心概念
talks about the core concepts
内置的分析策略、高级话题
talks about built in analyses advanced topics
你可以
you can go to
你可以点击 angr示例
you can click on examples
这里有一些具体有用有趣的例子
and there's just like examples that do specific useful         interesting things
这就是angr
that was angr
你应该熟悉ida、ghidra、binary ninja了
you're familiar with the Ida Ghidra binary Ninja
这些都支撑脚本扩展
these sort of things they're all scriptable
你也可以在其中进行静态分析
you can also do static analysis in them
binary ninja cloud不行
not binary Ninja cloud
要桌面版的binary ninja
but binary Ninja Desktop
然后，如果你有幸拥有源代码访问权限
and then if you have the Luxury of having source code      access
Clang和GCC也可以编写脚本
clang and gcc are scriptable as well
有很多
there are a lot
不能编写脚本，但可以使用它们来实现分析
or not scriptable but you can use them to implement        analyses
实际上，GCC已经进行了一些分析
in fact gcc will already do some analyses
如果你不安全的使用像strcpy之类的，它会警告你
it'll warn you if you're unsafely using stuff like strcpy in    certain situations
市面上有很多静态分析工具
there are a lot of static analysis tools out there
也许有一天我们会扩展这个模块
maybe one day we'll expand this module
或者可以分多个模块来覆盖它们
or maybe make it into multiple modules to cover many of  them
但是现在
but for now
这是对静态分析的快速概述
this is a very quick overview of static analysis
如果你对研究创建新的分析方法感兴趣的话
again if you're interested in doing research and creating   new analyses
给我发封邮件
shoot me an email
如果你能走到这一步
if you made it this far
你可以帮助创建程序分析的未来
you could help create the future of program analysis
下个视频见
see you in the next video